<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Posts on Tarik's Book Reviews</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Tarik's Book Reviews</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Decisive by Dan Heath and Chip Heath</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/decisive/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/decisive/</guid><description>It has been refreshing to read a well-written book for some time. Decisive will take its place in my top books. Let&amp;rsquo;s review it.
Over time, I started to dislike one thing in my decision-making journey: feeling stuck in binary choices. And time after time, I benefited more from the &amp;ldquo;AND&amp;rdquo; than the &amp;ldquo;OR&amp;rdquo; decisions. When people consulted me for their problems, I often saw this same problem in their decisions too.</description></item><item><title>The 5 Dysfunctions of a Team by Patrick Lencioni</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/five-dysfunctions-of-a-team/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/five-dysfunctions-of-a-team/</guid><description>My review of The 5 Dysfunctions of a Team by Patrick Lencioni
Great managers can detect the symptoms and signals of inefficiencies within their teams. They can also identify them in other teams, for the symptoms usually exhibit similar patterns. Detecting these signals is a critical step of the rest.
One typical signal is the absence of attention to the team results. The team individuals don&amp;rsquo;t pay attention and show passion towards their team goals.</description></item><item><title>The Amazon Way by John Rossman</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/amazons-way/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/amazons-way/</guid><description>My review of the book “Amazon Way” by John Rossman: What’s the simplest yet hardest reason behind Amazon’s success? I would answer it as defining straightforward principles and uncompromisingly executing them.
As I grow in my own career; every day, I am reminded of one of the most critical drivers of successful leadership, and that is the consistent expectation and execution of higher standards for your teams. Every small exception results in more exceptions.</description></item><item><title>Working With Emotional Intelligence by Daniel Goleman</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/working-with-emotional-intelligence/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/working-with-emotional-intelligence/</guid><description>Companies care about emotional intelligence more than technical knowledge (cognitive intelligence), but why?
The answer is hidden in the definition of “Emotional Intelligence,” which means to be able to recognize, express, and control your emotions. It also includes the ability to work with others.
Recognizing and controlling your emotions is not for drama but to understand what influences your feelings and how you can channel them for the better. For instance, you can use your fear to know if you successfully get of your comfort zone, and the same fear can also tell if you are too far from your comfort zone, which might hurt more than benefit.</description></item><item><title>The Language of Leadership by Joel Schwartzberg</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-language-of-leadership/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-language-of-leadership/</guid><description>My Review of the book &amp;ldquo;The Language of Leadership&amp;rdquo; Language is the essential skill of a leader. Using the power of language, leaders share their vision, address problems, and mobilize people. Effective communicators are exalted; ineffective communicators are excused.
There are two essential elements of effective communication: Purpose and Power. The purpose is the vision communicated in your message. The power is to grab and keep the attention of those who listen to you.</description></item><item><title>The Phoenix Project by Gene Kim, Kevin Behr, and George Spafford</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-phoenix-project/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-phoenix-project/</guid><description>My review of the book &amp;ldquo;The Phoenix Project.&amp;rdquo; Not everyone knows the pain behind the evolution of software development and operations of today&amp;rsquo;s more modern techniques and methodologies.
They are still not perfectly easy, but they were horrible back then. Agile SDLC, Scrum and Kanban, Continuous Delivery, Continuous Integration, and many others are not simply lip-services. They were developed after many long and painful experiences and still see revisions today.</description></item><item><title>The Hard Things About Hard Things by Ben Horowitz</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-hard-things-about-hard-things/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-hard-things-about-hard-things/</guid><description>My review of the book “The hard things about hard things” by Ben Horowitz. Do you feel like you don’t know what to do as the CEO of your company? Well, Ben Horowitz didn’t either. But what he saw in his career is that the great CEOs didn’t quit. It was not how much they knew but how courageous they were that mattered most of the time. Experience follows ambition.</description></item><item><title>The Culture Map by Erin Meyer</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-culture-map/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-culture-map/</guid><description>My book review of Culture Map by Erin Meyer: One book you must read before managing or doing business with people from other cultures.
Culture is not straightforward. What is respectful for others might not be for you. But, once you miss the difference there, all good intentions turn into bitter conflicts, literally for nothing. You lose trust, friendships, and businesses.
What defines proper communication is barely communication itself. It is not about talking directly or indirectly, as some cultures prefer.</description></item><item><title>Leading From the Middle by Scott Mautz</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/leading-from-the-middle/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/leading-from-the-middle/</guid><description>My review on “Leading from the Middle” book:
Are you suffocating when you do your management job because you feel like you are being pulled away in multiple directions? It is the case for many managers, partly because they lack the proper mindset or skillset or both, and that is okay. We will learn new things about our job for years to come. However, learning only on the act will potentially cause learning fatigue because of the emotional baggage that comes with constant failures.</description></item><item><title>Pre-suasion by Robert Cialdini</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/presuasion/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/presuasion/</guid><description>My review on Pre-suasion Book
How rational are we? What if someone tells us we are less rational than we think. In fact, a lot less rational we tend to believe. Pre-suasion is not telling it to us but trying to prove it with real-world examples and scientific evidence. The result? It is scary, real scary. One fact though, these techniques are not guaranteed to work all the time. They are to increase the persuasive power of your message.</description></item><item><title>The Mental Toughness Book by Damon Zahariades</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-mental-toughness-book/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-mental-toughness-book/</guid><description>My review of “Mental Toughness” book:
Life is hard. But, what makes it even harder is our perception of it. But if our perception can make it harder, can it make our life easier? It certainly can.
The more we get loose from the reality, more our frustrations grow that much because our expectations don’t match what is out there. In this subjectivity, we can also find strength and a sense of serenity.</description></item><item><title>Impossible to Ignore by Carmen Simon</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/impossible-to-ignore/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/impossible-to-ignore/</guid><description>I am still reading this book, and it is one of the most exciting books I am reading recently, so I decided to do a quick shoutout for it.
Tapping into human memories and becoming a part of their subconscious is a powerful way to deliver memorable messages. Once the message is memorable, it is more likely that people will act on your initial message. But how does that work?</description></item><item><title>Yes! 50 Scientifically Ways to Be Persuasive by Robert B. Cialdini</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/50-scientifically-ways-to-be-persuasive/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/50-scientifically-ways-to-be-persuasive/</guid><description>My review of the book &amp;ldquo;Yes! 50 Scientifically Ways to Be Persuasive.&amp;rdquo;
We both persuade people and get influenced by others, perhaps every single day, without even realizing it. And some of them are based on ethical principles. But some are not.
Knowing persuasion will make you more resilient against the dark ones. It will also make you more persuasive for your message.
Remember, though; these simple techniques are not to work 100% of the time, like almost everything else.</description></item><item><title>Make Your Point by Kevin Carroll and Bob Elliott</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/make-your-point/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/make-your-point/</guid><description>My Review of the book &amp;ldquo;Make Your Point&amp;rdquo;
Weak communication can cause you lose a HONDA CRV every week. Communication is crucial for success.
Take me for example. I have 10 meetings every day on average. Sometimes it is 14. Let’s make it a humble number. Take 5 meetings. Most of them have around 5 people on average and last for about an hour. Let’s take the 80$ per hour rate.</description></item><item><title>Win Bigly by Scott Adams</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/win-bigly/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/win-bigly/</guid><description>My review on the book “Win Bigly” by Scott Adams:
Persuasion is clearly crucial for success. It is everywhere. It is almost impossible to escape from it. We use it even we don’t realize it. It is fine until it is not. Some people engineer their persuasion skills. It is like fire. You can use it for cooking delicious food or hurting others.
Scott Adams explains the practical use of persuasion using Donald Trump as an example.</description></item><item><title>The Art of Thinking Clearly</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-art-of-thinking-clearly/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-art-of-thinking-clearly/</guid><description>My review for The art of thinking clearly
What if someone told us the filter we use to see the world is flawed big time? This book is that someone. We have lots of biases that shape our worldview.
Let’s take confirmation bias as an example. Two people with competing two ideas interpret the same data in a way supportive of their beliefs. Making this one up: Eating lettuce caused chickenpox for 0.</description></item><item><title>The Seven Things Your Team Needs to Hear You Say by David M. Dye</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-seven-things-your-team-needs-to-hear-you-say/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-seven-things-your-team-needs-to-hear-you-say/</guid><description>My review for “The seven things your team needs to hear you say it”
It is another book that will stay with me at the office as a constant reminder. It is a practical book. It gives simple actionable suggestions that you can start using right away. Before I tell you the 7 things, change in your current self can be instigated if you surround yourself with the right people, build the right environment with lots of cues, and decide on the right problem to start with.</description></item><item><title>The Courageous Cultures by Karin Hurt and David Dye</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-courageous-cultures/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-courageous-cultures/</guid><description>Courageous Cultures Book Review
You have probably heard of psychological safety. It is a place where people feel safe to speak up. However, it is mainly created by leaders. But even if this space is made, there will be people who won’t speak up. And it is the story of this book. Leaders, while creating psychological safety, will also need to develop courageous team players who are willing to speak up.</description></item><item><title>How to Fail at Almost Everything and Still Win Big by Scott Adams</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/how-to-fail-at-almost-everything-and-still-win-big/</guid><description>There are few books that I liked as much as Scott Adams’ book. I have found his mindset very close to mine, and the things he said in this book resonated with me for this reason. Unlike other books, I won’t list everything I liked in the book since it would be impossible for a LinkedIn post to cover them all. But there are a couple of things I especially liked in his mentality:</description></item><item><title>Multipliers by Liz Wiseman</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/multipliers/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/multipliers/</guid><description>Another day and another book review.
What if you start telling a fundamentally different idea to your set of beliefs you developed over the years as a manager: “Everyone is smart, and I will let them figure out.” This is the basic premise of the book Multipliers.
This idea comes with a lot of implicit actions. If you believe they are smart, you start changing your behaviors towards your teams:</description></item><item><title>Start With Why by Simon Sinek</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/start-with-why/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/start-with-why/</guid><description>The message of the book is straightforward. Start with Why instead of what and how. Several takeaways from the book:
You can constructively challenge presumptions and assumptions by exploring their reasons to exist. Asking why can reveal problems that are wasting resources. You can inspire people if you explain the why clearly to them. &amp;ldquo;Why&amp;rdquo; can help you find the people you need or join the groups you feel belong to.</description></item><item><title>Permission to Screw Up by Kristen Hadeed</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/permission-to-screw-up/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/permission-to-screw-up/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Permission to screw up&amp;rdquo; by Kristen Hadeed was a worthy two-day reading and fun get-away from more hardcore leadership books that I have been reading lately. The exciting aspect of this book is that it does not teach you anything new, perhaps. But it certainly makes you feel what leadership is about, and sometimes, it is more critical than just knowing. The book teaches you not the hardship but the magnitude of it that comes with leadership.</description></item><item><title>Essentialism by Greg McKeown</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/essentialism/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/essentialism/</guid><description>Today I have finished “Essentialism,” and here are my thoughts about it in the essential amount:
The essence of essentialism is to say either “HELL YES” or “No” to any responsibility life throws at us. Meaning that the criteria for saying “yes” must be a high return on investment and clarity, or it is simply a “no.” The reason is simple: You don&amp;rsquo;t have enough time for everything, and you need to find the impactful work that creates the most significant impact to optimally use your time, body, and mind.</description></item><item><title>The Next Level by Scott Eblin</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-next-level/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/the-next-level/</guid><description>When I like a book, the first thing I do after reading it is to check to referenced books at the end of it. By doing that, I end up reading books that I like, at least most of the time.
Today, I want to share my thoughts on “The Next Level” by Scott Eblin. It was referenced in the “Hacking Executive Leadership” book. When stepping up into the next level in your career, we need to pick up new skills and mindsets and let go of other ones in three areas:</description></item><item><title>Leading Change by John P. Kotter</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/leading-change/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/leading-change/</guid><description>I finished reading &amp;ldquo;Leading Change&amp;rdquo; by John P. Kotter this week. Here is my quick review of this book.
Change is inevitable, but it gets complicated as its size and interconnectedness increase. Inertia sets in overtime. Long-standing successful companies develop managers who keep the system stable instead of leaders. People lose sight of external dynamics changing the world around them. And, companies lose their competitiveness dramatically in this fast-changing world. It is changing because of the competition.</description></item><item><title>Hacking Executive Leadership by Emily Sander</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/hacking-executive-leadership/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/hacking-executive-leadership/</guid><description>Hacking Executive Leadership is one of the books I have enjoyed reading for some time. It offers concise suggestions to some of the most common leadership problems. These problems include:
Handling failure Managing your self-image and beliefs Indecisiveness Perfection Hiring and Firing Varying natures of people around Perhaps the most compelling part of the book is the mindset and perspectives it provides. It takes failure, self-criticizing, and self-worth from different aspects and approaches them from a pragmatic point of view, and uses assuring yet natural language.</description></item><item><title>Understanding Variation by Donald J. Wheeler</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/understanding-variation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/understanding-variation/</guid><description>Another fantastic read this week. How do you make sense from various data points? Comparing one number to another is weak and limited many times as it won&amp;rsquo;t give enough context. Hence, it would be best if you had a complete picture to compare the numbers in a more global context. For this need, the time series plots come in. But now you have more data to analyze. How do you distinguish signal from noise?</description></item><item><title>Six Sigma for Everyone by Geroge Eckes</title><link>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/six-sigma-for-everyone/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://www.bookreviews.io/posts/six-sigma-for-everyone/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Six Sigma for Everyone&amp;rdquo; book was another excellent read for me this week. I particularly love books that also provide the history of the subject, and George Eckes did exactly that. I was actually surprised to know that Six Sigma was developed by a smart engineer in my old company Motorola Solutions. No wonder that company has been defeating many market ups and downs for more than 90 years. The innovative spirit and the management support for quality pay off in the long term.</description></item></channel></rss>